<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Quentin Geissmann</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Quentin Geissmann</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Quentin Geissmann</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sticky Pi</title>
      <link>/project/sticky-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sticky-pi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Millipede</title>
      <link>/project/millipede/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/millipede/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The mill on pedals!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO The Millipde in image with a caption / video&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-wondermill&#34;&gt;The wondermill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, I purchased a &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thewondermill.com/index.php/module/statics/action/view_listing/page/53&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wondermill Junior&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, which is a basically a benchtop hand-powered mill.
The &amp;ndash; comedic and exhaustive &amp;ndash; promotional videos do a good job at promoting this thing of beauty, so I will jump straight to the point.
I was using it quite often, especially to make pea and buckwheat flour &amp;ndash; or peanut butter and sesame paste, using the stainless steel stones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point I love about the mill:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fresh flower &amp;ndash; one can keep seeds and mill them on demand which increases tastes and shelflife.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Money saving &amp;ndash;  often, buying a bulk of seeds is a lot cheaper than flour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Versatility &amp;ndash; one does not need to store both flour and grains of the same crop. One can also make flour of less industrial (&lt;em&gt;e.g.&lt;/em&gt; foraged goods)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exercise &amp;ndash; it is a nice way to move a bit after a long day of work, and it is silent enough that one can listen to a podcast at the same time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Romanticism &amp;ndash; it is elegantly minimalist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-pedals&#34;&gt;Why pedals?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I had guests, I asked them for a hand to mill as it gets rather physical after 10 min non-stop.
Although I personally find that fun, my &amp;ldquo;sweating before eating&amp;rdquo; policy was not unanimously acclaimed &amp;ndash; sad days.
In addition, some people of smaller stature would not even manage to actually mill hard grains.
Therefore, I started a crazy project aiming at putting the mill on pedals &amp;ndash; thus keeping its positive attributes whilst making it more efficient.
I thought it would be fun to share the latest version of my design my design with the other lunatics crawling the web.
The wondermill is already quite expensive, and I was reluctant to spend any more money.
My philosophy for this project was, therefore, to recycle/repurpose as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this page, I just put together the prerequisites as well as minimal assembly instructions and blueprints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-prerequisites&#34;&gt;Project prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic woodworking (tenon and mortices).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic 3D printing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very basic knowledge of bicycle mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 3m of sturdy wood (e.g. 3x2 construction timber, I found mine in a skip)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An old bicycle frame with crank and pedals attached (ideally a broken rusty vintage one. I found mine actually abandoned in a wood)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A chain, derailleur and cassette&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A 3D printed adaptor to fit the cassette on the mill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The wondermill itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pair of G clamps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools and consumables:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wood saw, mallet, chisels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wood glue and clamps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hard string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 screws for wood&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hacksaw and file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;assembly&#34;&gt;Assembly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the design will depend on what material you find and, I hope, your own improvements/adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-final-product&#34;&gt;The final product&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO pict (The final assembled millipede)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-holder&#34;&gt;The holder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The holder is the wooden chassis that holds everything together.
The idea is to put together something with these dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todo drawing (millipede holder)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother introduced me to woodwork and to the soothing &amp;ndash; and weirdly addictive &amp;ndash; voice of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/PaulSellersWoodwork/playlists&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Paul Sellers&lt;/a&gt;, which I highly recommend.
I wanted to start my woodworking training with this project.
The important point here is that you want &lt;strong&gt;something quite sturdy&lt;/strong&gt; as you will sit and move around.
If your structure is not rigid enough, the torque on the mill, especially on hard grains, may also warp it, making it less efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bicycle-and-derailleur&#34;&gt;The bicycle and derailleur&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this project, we just need the rear part of the frame: the one that would hold the saddle and the back wheel.
I used a hacksaw to cut the rest off &amp;ndash; consistently with my effort to minimise the design.
Some people find it hard to balance without a handlebar, so you may want to keep the front of the bike for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to avoid screws when possible. Therefore, I used a chisel to dig groves where the bike should go. I then used hard strings/rope to keep the bike in place.
I like the simplicity of string and the possibility to remove it (e.g. to for cleaning or transport):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todo picture of the holder&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first prototype I put together did not have a derailleur, which was a mistake. Then the chain did jump a lot especially on large hard grains (e.g. corn), and it was effectively impossible to tune the gear ratio.
Therefore I added a derailleur to the current version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO derailleur fig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I have cut a small piece of wood to fix he derailleur using its hanger and a couple of screws/bolts.
I first clamped the support until I was happy with its position, and then glued it.
This way, we do not risk damaging the holder and we could relatively simply change the derailleur or its position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mounting-the-mill&#34;&gt;Mounting the mill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than using a single sprocket (such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thewondermill.com/index.php/module/statics/action/view_listing/page/58&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the one sold by the wondermill people&lt;/a&gt;), I opted for a cassette, so I can play around with the gear ratio according to what mill.
I 3d printed an adaptor for a shimano cassette that fits the shaft of the wondemill:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todo drawing of the adaptor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, instead of screwing or bolting the mill directly to the holder, I put it on a separate board and I clamp the board (using G clamps) when I mill.
This allows me to clean the mill or move it left to right to line up the gear I want:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todo pict of the board to screw it in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This design also makes it the millipede modular so that we can remove the mill and other rotation/based instead. For instance, I have put together an millipede-powered apple-crusher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you had fun reading about the millipede and that you try building your own and do not hesistate to send me some feed back!
I also hope the wondermill company comes accross this post and strat sending me freebies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethomics</title>
      <link>/project/rethomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/rethomics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethoscope</title>
      <link>/project/ethoscope/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/ethoscope/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sleep in fruit flies</title>
      <link>/project/sleep-drosophila/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sleep-drosophila/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sleep is a fascinating mystery that has bemused thinkers since the dawn of civilisations. Scientifically, the formalisation of sleep as an observable behaviour has been a conceptual milestone, which has enabled researchers to address the question of its ubiquity and ultimately led to the discovery of sleep-like states in most animal phyla. The fruit fly &lt;em&gt;Drosophila melanogaster&lt;/em&gt; has long been at the vanguard of the discovery of many biological processes. During my PhD, I worked on the quantification and alteration and of sleep in &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt;. You can read more about my work in my thesis: &lt;a href=&#34;https://spiral.imperial.ac.uk/bitstream/10044/1/69514/3/Geissmann-Q-2018-PhD-Thesis.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;High-throughput Recording, Analysis andManipulation of Sleep in Drosophila&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenCFU</title>
      <link>/project/opencfu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/opencfu/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snail backpack</title>
      <link>/project/snail-back-pack/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/snail-back-pack/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
